Tao Chen

Curriculum Vitae



Personal Profile

- Proactive and creative researcher.
- Research experience with working in independent or collaborative research projects.
- Teaching experience with undergraduate and postgraduate students.
- Effective administrator and organizer.

Research Interests

My research has been on *Software Engineering*, including but not limited to, *Performance Engineering*, *Search-based Software Engineering*, *Cloud Computing* and *Services Computing*. I am particularly interested in engineering *Self-Adaptive Software Systems*, understanding their runtime behaviors and applying them in cloud-based, service-oriented and distributed environment. Most of my work leverages *Natural Computation*, *Machine Learning* and *Economic Theory* to tackle the problems (please see my publications for details).

Education

2012–2016 **Ph.D.**, School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK. Thesis Title: Self-Aware and Self-Adaptive Autoscaling for Cloud-Based Services Area of Study: Systems and Software Engineering

2009–2010 **M.Sc.**, School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK, Distinction.

Dissertation Title: Scalable Service-Oriented Replication in the Cloud Area of Study: Systems and Software Engineering

2006–2009 **B.Sc.**, School of Computing, Birmingham City University, Birmingham, UK, First class.

Average Score: overall 78%, 80% for final project Area of Study: Systems and Software Engineering

Employment History

Vocational

- 2016-present Research Fellow, Centre of Excellence for Research in Computational Intelligence and Applications (CERCIA), School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham, Birmingham.
 - Conducted research in the research projects.
 - Produced scientific results either independently or collaboratively.
 - 2013–2015 Research Associate, School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham, Birmingham.
 - Leaded tasks in a specific work package of the research projects.
 - Assisted in organizing workshop with collaborators and partners.
 - Worked with partners to write scientific papers.
 - 2013–2015 **Teaching Assistant**, School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham, Birmingham.
 - Assisted in designing coursework.
 - Provided questions/answers sessions to undergraduate and postgraduate students.
 - Marked coursework.
 - 2011–2012 **Software Engineer**, *Skillstream Ltd*, London.
 - 2012-2013 (part time)
 - (full time) Following on the Scrum agile methodology, I was part of the 'Sprint' team responsible for analyzing users' requirements, developing software service, testing and deploying the system on the geographically distributed infrastructure. I was also involved in debugging and maintenance tasks.

Internship

- 2008 Software Engineer, Pudong Development Bank, China.
- 2007 **Software Engineer**, BOAO Ltd, China.

Research Experience

- 2016-present Researcher (theme leader), Dynamic Adaptive Automated Software Engineering (DAASE), Grant No. EP/J017515/1, £6,834,903 funded by EPSRC.
 - Investigated effective optimization and modeling approaches for self-adaptive software systems.
 - Created synergy between software engineering and computational intelligence.
 - 2015–2016 Co-principal investigator, Ecology Inspired Self-Aware Autoscaling Supporting Elastic Cloud-Based Services, £8,000 funded by Ramsay Research Funding Schema, School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham.
 - Leaded all the tasks of the whole project.
 - Identified the benefits of ecology for cloud computing.
 - Formulated and modeled the services in cloud using ecological principles.
 - Proposed architecture for ecological cloud computing.
 - 2014–2015 **Researcher**, Engineering Proprioception in Computing Systems (EPiCS), Grant No. FP7-ICT-2009-5, €681,385 funded by the FET proactive initiative "Self-Awareness in Autonomic Systems" by the European Union 7th Framework Programme.
 - Leaded the task for architecting self-aware systems using self-aware patterns.
 - Categorized the architectural primitives for self-aware systems.
 - Proposed comprehensive methodology to assist in developing self-aware systems.

- 2013 **Researcher**, *Least Cost Fulfilment*, £26,415 funded by EPSRC KTS (Knowledge Transfer Secondments).
 - Leaded the task for modeling performance of the cloud-based application.
 - Assisting in determining the demand of cloud resources while minimizing the cost.

Refereed Publications

Journal Articles

- TSE **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Self-Adaptive and Online QoS Modeling for Cloud-Based Software Services, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, vol. 43, no. 5, 2017. (Top 5 most popular article in IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering 2017)
- TSC **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Self-Adaptive Trade-off Decision Making for Autoscaling Cloud-Based Services, IEEE Transactions on Services Computing, 2015, doi:10.1109/TSC.2015.2499770.
- IEEE COM **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Towards A Smarter Cloud: Self-Aware Autoscaling of Cloud Configurations and Resources, IEEE Computer, vol. 48, no. 9, 2015.
- IEEE COM P.R. Lewis, A. Chandra, F. Faniyi, K. Glette, **T. Chen**, R. Bahsoon, J. Torresen and X. Yao, Architectural Aspects of Self-Aware and Self-Expressive Computing Systems: From Psychology to Engineering, IEEE Computer, vol. 48, no. 8, 2015.
 - INS T. Chen, R. Bahsoon and A-R H. Tawil. Scalable Service-Oriented Replication with Flexible Consistency Guarantee in the Cloud. Information Sciences, Elsevier, vol. 264, 2014.

Conference Proceedings

- UCC 2014 **T. Chen**, R. Bahsoon and X. Yao. Online QoS Modeling in the Cloud: A Hybrid and Adaptive Multi-Learners Approach. In proceeding of the 7th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Utility and Cloud Computing (UCC2014), London, UK. 2014. (acceptance rate 19%)
- SEAMS 2014 **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Symbiotic and Sensitivity-Aware Architecture for Globally-Optimal Benefit in Self- Adaptive Cloud. In proceeding of the 9th International Symposium on Software Engineering for Adaptive and Self-Managing Systems (SEAMS), in conjunction with the 36th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), India, 2014. (acceptance rate 22%)
- SEAMS 2013 **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Self-Adaptive and Sensitivity-Aware QoS Modeling for the Cloud. In proceeding of the 8th International ACM/IEEE Symposium on Software Engineering for Adaptive and Self-Managing Systems (SEAMS), in conjunction with the 35th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), San Francisco, CA, 2013.(acceptance rate 27%)
 - ICCS 2013 T. Chen, R. Bahsoon and G. Theodoropoulos. A Decentralized Architecture for Dynamic QoS Optimization in Cloud-based DDDAS. In proceeding of International Conference on Computational Science, Procedia of Computer Science, Elsevier Science, 2013. (acceptance rate 30%)
- IEEE CLOUD **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Scalable Service Oriented Replication in the Cloud. 2011 In proceeding of the 4th IEEE International Conference on Cloud Computing, Washington D.C., USA, 2011. (acceptance rate 21%)

Book Chapters

- **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Bridging Ecology and Cloud: Transposing Ecological Perspective to Enable Better Cloud Autoscaling, in the book of Software Architecture for Big Data and the Cloud, Morgan Kaufmann, 2017.
- **T. Chen**, F. Faniyi, and R. Bahsoon. Design Patterns and Primitives: Introduction of Components and Patterns for Self-Aware Computing Systems, in the book of Self-Aware Computing Systems, Elsevier, 2016.

Technical Reports

- **T. Chen** and R. Bahsoon. Survey and Taxonomy of Self-Aware and Self-Adaptive Autoscaling Systems in the Cloud. Technical Report, arXiv:1609.03590 [cs.SE], 2016.
- **T. Chen**, F. Faniyi, R. Bahsoon, P.R. Lewis, X. Yao, L.L. Minku, and L. Esterle. The Handbook of Engineering Self-Aware and Self-Expressive Systems. Technical Report, arXiv:1409.1793 [cs.SE], 2014.

Submitted for Publication

- **T. Chen**, K. Li, R. Bahsoon and X.Yao. FEMOSAA: Feature Guided and Knee Driven Multi-Objective Optimization for Self-Adaptive Software at Runtime.
- **T. Chen**, S. Wang, R. Bahsoon and X.Yao. To Adapt or Not to Adapt: Technical Debt Driven Runtime Adaptation for Self-Adaptive Software.

Teaching Experience

Academic Supervision

- 2017–present Dalia Sobhy, Economic and Machine Learning Driven Self-Adaptive Architecture Diversity in IoT, Ph.D. in Software Engineering and Computer Science (co-supervised with Dr. Rami Bahsoon)
- 2017–present Satish Kumar, Evolutionary Multi-Tenanted Service Composition at SaaS, Ph.D. in Software Engineering and Computer Science (co-supervised with Dr. Rami Bahsoon)
 - 2017 Taiyang Guo, Cloud Instance Selection using Parallel K-Mean Clustering and Hadoop, M.Sc. in Advanced Computer Science
- 2016—present Carlos Joseph Mera Gomez, Technical Debt Models for the Cloud, Ph.D. in Software Engineering and Computer Science (co-supervised with Dr. Rami Bahsoon)
 - 2016 Marcus Chon Kit Ng, Multi Populations with Dynamic Diversity Levels for Dynamic Optimization, M.Sc. in Advanced Computer Science (co-supervised with Prof. Xin Yao)

Lecture Assisting

- 2014–2015 Software Engineering II (postgraduate students)
- 2014–2015 Fundamental Software Engineering II (undergraduate and postgraduate students)
- 2013–2014 Software Engineering II (postgraduate students)
- 2013–2014 Fundamental Software Engineering II (undergraduate and postgraduate students)

Administration Experience

Research Committee Member

- 2017–present Voted on funding applications for Research Committee funds.
 - Discussed research issues during committee meetings.

Publicity Chair of SE group/EU project

- 2013–2016 Engaged in the management for publicity of the Software Engineering Research Group, University of Birmingham.
 - Assisted in the organization of workshop with project collaborators.

Selected Talks

- 2016 Invited talk at seminar of School of Computing and Communication, Lancaster University
- 2015 Talk at seminar of Software Engineering Research Group, University of Birmingham
- 2014 Talk at seminar of EPSRC project: Dynamic Adaptive Automated Software Engineering, University of Birmingham
- 2014 Talk at seminar of Software Engineering Research Group, University of Birmingham
- 2014 Talk at workshop of EU project: Engineering Proprioception in Computing Systems, Botanic Garden, Birmingham
- 2013 Talk at seminar of EU project: Engineering Proprioception in Computing Systems, University of Birmingham

Grants, Awards and Scholarships

- 2015 School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham, Paul and Yuanbi Ramsay Research Grant (£8,000).
- 2014 ACM Special Interest Group on Software Engineering's (SIGSOFT) outstanding student researcher travel award (£630).
- 2013 ACM Special Interest Group on Software Engineering's (SIGSOFT) outstanding student researcher travel award (£527).
- 2012 School of Computer Science, fully-funded University of Birmingham Ph.D. scholarship for international students. (selecting only one student each year to fund £28,210 per annum for three years)
- 2009 School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham outstanding M.Sc. student scholarship (£3,000).
- 2006 School of Computing, Birmingham City University best international undergraduate student award and scholarship (£9,000).

Professional Services

Memberships

2013-2016 IEEE student member

2016-now IEEE member

2013-2016 ACM student member

Editorial Board Member/Reviewer of Journals

Journal of Systems and Software

Information Sciences

Services Transactions on Internet of Things (STIOT)

PC member/Reviewer of Conferences

IEEE World Congress on Services, 2017

S2 International Conference on Internet of Things, 2016

IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2016

IEEE Services 2016 Emerging Track: Big Data Software Engineering for Cloud, Edge Computing and Mobility

International Conference on Services Computing, 2015

European Conference on Software Architecture, 2015

International Conference on Services Computing, 2014

Technical Proficiency

Programming and Frameworks

Java, Javascript, Shell script, Actionscript, Flex, HTML, SQL, J2EE, JDBC, Hibernate, Structs, Velocity, Wicket, Spring, Liquidbase, Axis2, Encog, LATEX

Software and Virtualization

Xen, Apache Tomcat, MySQL, PostgresSQL, Oracle, Apache

Software Development Control and Management

SVN, Git, Ant, Maven, Jenkins

Methodology and Analytical Notations

UML, Scrum, Database Analytics, ATAM

References

Rami Bahsoon.

Senior Lecturer

School of Computer Science, University of Birmingham

Phone: +44 (0) 121 414 4770 | Email: r.bahsoon@cs.bham.ac.uk

Xin Yao.

Professor

 $School\ of\ Computer\ Science,\ University\ of\ Birmingham$

Phone: +44 (0) 121 414 3747 | Email: x.yao@cs.bham.ac.uk

Mirco Musolesi.

Reader

Department of Geography, University College London

Phone: +44 (0) 207 679 0567 | Email: m.musolesi@ucl.ac.uk